Finding Aid for Medical Scientist Training Program (University of Michigan) Records 1978-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Medical Scientist Training Program (University of Michigan) records 1978-1996
University of Michigan. Medical Scientist Training Program.
2 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
A dual degree program established in 1979 between the Medical School and the graduate school allowing students to complete the requirements for the Ph.D. and M.D. degree on an accelerated pace aimed at producing research scientists. Records include planning, operation, and policy committee minutes; admissions and recruiting material; curriculum files, and budgetary material and grant applications.
97138 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred by the Medical Scientist Training Program in April 1997 (Donor No. 8585 ). Additional records were received from George DeMuth (Donor No. 8603 ).
The collection is open for research with the exception of student records and certain committee records which are restricted in accordance with university policy and applicable law.
The University of Michigan Medical School's Medical Scientist Training Program (MSTP) is a highly competitive dual degree program resulting in a MD from the Medical School and a Ph.D. from the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. The purpose of the program is to prepare graduates for biomedical research careers. The program was established in December 1979, and began operations on July 1, 1980. The program coordinates recruiting, financing, curriculum and monitoring for the fellows. The program is not degree granting, and does not offer any courses. The program takes approximately seven years to complete. There were four students in the first group of fellows in 1980. Since that year, the number of incoming fellows averages between six and nine fellows per year. As of 1998, there were 68 graduates of the program.
Most of the funding for the program is provided by a grant from the National Institute of Health, through the National Institute of General Medical Sciences. The first grant was approved in 1980, with subsequent renewals in 1985, 1990, and 1995. The bulk of the grant provides for fellowships for each student, including full tuition and stipend.
The Operating Committee is the chief advisory committee of the MSTP. The committee also functions as the advisory admissions committee. The committee advises the Program Director and Associate Directors of the program.
General oversight of the program is performed by the Policy Committee. The purpose of the committee is to review the annual activities of MSTP, and to recommend policies for those matters that may cross departmental, and/or medical school - graduate school jurisdiction.
For further current information consult the MSTP web page at the following URL: http://www.med.umich.edu/medschool/mstp/
Directors of the Medical Scientist Training Program
1979-1992 George R. DeMuth
1992-1995 Roderick Nairn
1995-1996 David R. Engelke
1996-present Ronald J. Koenig
The records of the Medical Scientist Training Program are predominantly agendas and minutes of committee meetings. The collection is divided into five series: Administrative, Admissions and Recruiting, Committee Agendas and Minutes, Correspondence, and Curriculum and unit publications. The bulk of the collection is dated from 1979 through 1989.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Medical Scientist Training Program.; Medical scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Research--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series is comprised of two major areas: funding and management matters. An NIH grant application for 1990-1995 comprises the major part of the Funding subseries. Included in the General folders is the report produced for the NIH site visit in 1994, for the renewal of the grant. A small amount of correspondence regarding program expenditures and stipends during the period from 1986 to 1993 is included. A Program Management folder contains job descriptions, a management schedule, and recommendations resulting from an administrative review. These papers provide background for the policy procedures and decisions of the program.
  - George DeMuth 1974-1983 (Box 1)
    (includes CV)
  - Funding and Budget (Box 1)
  - General 1986-1994 (Box 1)
  - NIH grant application 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - General 1978-1986, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Grant Materials 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Handbook 1980 (Box 1)
  - Minority Access to Research Careers (MARC) Materials 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Program Management 1984-1991 (Box 1)
  - Proposal For Development 1990 (Box 1)
  - Space Renovation 1984 (Box 1)
- Admissions and Recruiting
  Admissions and Recruiting contains a report from 1985, forms, and recruiting materials for MSTP for the period from 1980 to 1992. The series also includes lists of incoming fellows for the years 1990-1992 and 1995-1996. The recruiting materials are helpful for providing background and insight into the program.
  - Admissions Procedures and Admitted Fellows 1985 (Box 1)
  - Applicants 1990 (Box 3)
    [RESTRICTED]
  - Applicants Aggregate Information 1979-1990 (Box 1)
  - Applicant Information 1981-1985 (Box 3)
  - Recruiting Materials 1980 (Box 1)
- Committee Agendas and Minutes
  Committee Agendas and Minutes is organized according to Committee names and by their activities such as reporting and retreats. The Committees are Policy Committee, Program Committee, Review Committee, and Social Sciences Committee.
  The Planning Committee met during 1979 to discuss the implementation of the program. The Operating Committee is the chief advisory committee of the program, and also serves as the advisory admissions committee. The subseries contains agendas and minutes from meetings, 1979 through 1989. The committee is composed of one representative from each degree granting graduate program participating in MSTP, two MSTP fellows, a clinical faculty member, and the Program and Associate Directors. The committee meets generally six to seven times per year.
  The purpose of the Review Committee was to review the progress of the program and to plan for its future. The committee met between late 1983 through May 1984, releasing its report on June 1, 1984. The Policy Committee performs the general oversight of the program. The committee also addresses issues that cross departmental boundaries and/or medical school - graduate school jurisdiction. The subseries includes the minutes for meetings from 1980 to 1985, with the exception of 1982. The committee is composed of the department chairmen, two inter-collegiate doctoral program directors, and the deans of the graduate and medical schools. The committee meets on an as-needed basis. The Program Committee contains no minutes or agendas, but includes correspondence relating to preparations for the annual scientific retreats and social events.
  Some of the records in the record group are restricted in order to protect individual privacy. The unrestricted committee materials are useful for observing the growth of the program from its inception, as well as the analysis and future planning from reviews.
  - Operating Committee, 6 folders
    - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2055 ]
    - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2057 ]
    - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January, 1, 2059 ]
    - 1985 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2060 ]
    - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2062 ]
    - 1988-1990 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2065 ]
  - Planning Committee, 5 folders
    - May 16, 1979 (Box 1)
    - July 5 to July 26, 1979 (Box 1)
    - August 7 to August 30, 1979 (Box 1)
    - September 13 to November 28, 1979 (Box 3)
      [RESTRICTED; Attachment to minutes of September 20; until January 1, 2054 ]
  - Policy Committee
    - February 14, 1980 (Box 1)
    - January 13, 1981 (Box 1)
    - March 22, 1983 (Box 1)
    - January 16, 1984 (Box 1)
    - January 12, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Policy Committee 1980 (Box 1)
  - Program Committee 1990 (Box 1)
  - Program Committee
    - Annual MSTP Scientific Retreat correspondence, circa 1995 (Box 1)
    - Reports/Proposals by Committees 1988-1991 (Box 1)
    - Retreat 1986 (Box 1)
  - Review Committee, 4 folders
    - November 1983-February 1984 (Box 1)
    - March 1984-May 1984 (Box 1)
    - Committee Report June 1, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from March 16, 1984 (Box 3)
      [Restricted until January 1, 2059 ]
  - Social Sciences Committee 1985-1986 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is primarily a record of founder George DeMuth's communication regarding the support of MSTP candidates and students. This includes assistance in locating aid, providing recommendations, and mediation of various faculty/student communication issues. Another well represented activity is DeMuth's promotion of the newly developed program to other members of U-M's Medical School faculty and members of the medical field at large.
  - 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1975-1993, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Curriculum
  Curriculum contains correspondence from 1978 to 1986, arranged in chronological order, relating to scheduling conflicts effecting the fellows in the program, and correspondence between Rackham and the Medical School concerning special waivers and requirements for the fellows. Also included are the mentor lists for the fellows in MSTP for the years 1984-1990, as well as 1993.
  - Departmental correspondence March 6, 1978-September 5, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Grades for Biological Chemistry 580 November 12, 1981 (Box 3)
    [Restricted until January 1, 2056 ]
  - Medical Scholars Program 1979 (Box 2)
  - Mentor Lists 1984-1990, 1993 (Box 2)
- Publications
  The Publications series includes general program brochures, invitations, and programs for the Scientific Retreat from 1990 through 1996.
  - Unit Publications
    - Brochures 1985-1997, undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Invitations 1987 (Box 4)
    - Programs
      - Scientific Retreat: Programs and Proceedings, 1990-1996, 4 folders (Box 4)